I bow to all the seekers of truth.
我向所有真理求道者敬禮。
That’s a very interesting subject that has been given to Me to talk to you people because
讓我為大家談論這個話題，是非常有趣的 ，因為
I have been always worried about the IAS, IPS, and other Government servants, very much
我一直很擔心IAS，IPS和其他政府公務員
worried because I have known the kind of life My husband was leading.
擔心是因為我知道我丈夫領導的那種生活。
And I used to think: if these new people, who have come to the services, to the Government
而我曾經想過：如果這些新人，他們來到這裡為政府服務，
service, we have to tell them the dangers that are ahead of them.
我們必須告訴他們前面的危險。
Because we don’t know what is the subtle system within us, which works.
因為我們不知道我們內裡的精微系統是什麼，如何操作。
And in the subtle system, when we lead this kind of a very speedy, intensive life, it
當我們引入這種非常迅速密集的生活，在精微系統中，它就會出現
has a defect.
毛病。
It has a defect you can see in the chart.
在圖表中你可以看到它有一個的毛病。
They have shown the, they have shown the subtle system which works it out.
他們展示了，他們展示了一個微妙的系統。
So we have a center here on the crossing of the optic chiasma.
這裡在視交叉中心有一個交匯點。
These, this center is very important because we react with this.
這個中心很重要，因我們以和這個作出反應。
We react to everything.
我們對一切都有反應
By this reaction we create a problem within ourselves.
但這些反應，會產生出我們內在的問題。
And this reaction comes to us because we do not know how to go beyond the mind.
這種反應因為我們不懂得如何超越思維而來到我們。
Every time we are looking at something, we react.
每當我們看到某些東西時，我們都會做出反應。
We look at someone, we react.
我們看一些人，我們做出反應。
But we cannot just watch.
但我們不能只是看著。
We cannot be just the witness.
我們不能只是靜觀。
If we could be the witness, it will not have any effect on us.
如果我們可以作旁觀者，它將不會對我們產生任何影響。
But we cannot be.
但我們不能夠。
That’s the trouble when this center is very active.
當這個中心非常活躍時，就會變成問題。
We call it as Agnya chakra, where the two optic nerves meet.
兩個是神經的交匯點，我們稱之為額輪Agnya。
At the crossing point, this center is placed.
在交匯點，位於中心。
Even Jung has said that, “You have to go beyond your thoughts and that you have to
甚至榮格也曾說過，「你必須超越自己的思維，而必須達到
become thoughtlessly aware.”
無思慮的醒覺」。
Even in our Shastras is it written that, “You have to have Nirvichar Samadhi,” is without
也有記載到即使我們在頂輪，「你必須無思慮醒覺」
thought and the another is Nirvikalpa Samadhi.
沒有思維，「另一個是無疑惑的醒覺」
Now even Einstein has said that, “You have to go beyond the mind to reach the torsion
甚至愛因斯坦都說過，「你必須超越頭腦才能達到扭力場
area,” he calls.
他這樣說。
When he was searching for his Theory of Relativity, he found it was difficult.
當他在尋找他的相對論時，他遇到難處。
He couldn’t find it.
他找不到。
He got very tired.
他很累。
He went into his garden and was playing with soap bubbles like a child.
他走進他的花園，像孩子一樣玩肥皂泡。
Then he says, “Suddenly from somewhere else it dawned upon me this Theory of Relativity.”
然後他說，「突然間相對論就出現了。」
He calls it openly as a torsion area and this torsion area we have to touch instead of ourselves
他把它稱為扭力場區，這個扭力場我們必須觸摸而不是自己
thinking all the time and reacting.
一直在思考和反應。
Because as a result of that what happens we should see.
因為我們應該看到發生了什麼。
What happens is that our movement on the autonomous nervous system goes to the right side.
會發生什麼是我們在自主神經系統上的運動走向右側。
The right side, it’s very good otherwise: A person looks very impressive.
右脈，是很好的，使人看起來非常令人印象深刻。
He can oppress other.
他可以壓迫其他人。
He can be aggressive.
他可以很有攻擊性。
He can be very systematic.
他可以非常系統化。
All these things can be there but it has a reaction.
所有這些都可以存在，但它有反作用。
The reaction is horrible because this right side affects our liver to begin with.
反作用很可怕，因為這個右傾會影響我們的肝臟。
Now the liver is called ‘liver’ because live, we live because of liver only.
現在肝臟被稱為「Liver」，因為活著(live)，我們 靠肝臟活著。
That’s why it’s called ‘liver’.
這就是它被稱為「肝臟(liver)」的原因。
This liver gets affected and there is no actually treatment we should say in the medical science
肝臟受到影響，在醫學上並沒治療法實際
for liver.
用於肝臟。
They can replace it with a pig’s liver or some liver like that.
他們可以用豬或類似的肝臟代替它。
But otherwise, there is no way out.
但除此之外，並無他法。
But we are the ones we are spoiling this liver ourself by creating tremendous heat in the
但我們卻製造巨大的熱來破壞自己的
liver.
肝臟。
This special liver has got a capacity to absorb heat and release heat into the blood stream
肝臟有特殊的功能，可吸收並排出血液中的熱
and then, you see, it gets relieved of it.
然後你看到，它肝臟得到緩解。
But when it is too much, when the liver is too much full of heat then it cannot give
但是當太多時，當肝臟充滿了太多的熱量，它就無法
up that heat.
排出熱。
Then heat, this heat, heat starts traveling upward.
然後這個熱開始向上游。
It can go to the right lung.
它可以去右邊肺部。
It can go to the heart.
它可以走向心臟。
Now imagine, right lung means asthma.
現在想像一下，右肺代表著哮喘。
Simple thing is asthma.
簡單的事就是哮喘。
Then it goes to the heart.
然後它走向心臟。
There’s a young boy, say of twenty one years or so, up to that age.
例如一個年輕的男孩，到21歲左右，在哪個年紀。
He starts playing cricket, tennis, and drinks a lot.
他打板球、打網球同時又喝很多酒。
Then he gets a massive heart attack.
之後他會患上大型的心臟病。
It’s fatal.
這是致命的。
He cannot live.
他不能活下去。
Then it affects as I told you other organs also.
如果所說，之後它影響其他器官。
This heat goes to the pancreas causing diabetes of a very serious nature, not of a mild nature
這熱會傳到胰腺，引起非常嚴重的糖尿病，不是溫和性的
but a very serious nature.
而非常嚴重的。
Then this heat passes down to the spleen.
然後這熱會傳到脾臟。
In the spleen, it gives you blood cancer.
在脾臟，它會使你患上血癌。
This is all possible for all right sided people, I am telling you.
我告訴你，這對所有右傾的人都可能發生的。
That’s why I was worried that people who are, according to Me, are the spine of our
這就是為什麼我那麼擔心我國的
country.
要員。
They are the spine of our country.
他們是我國的支柱。
They should not get out of life because of too much of strain and stress on their mind.
他們不應因過多的緊張和壓力而失去生命。
Now then it goes to the kidneys.
之後熱進入腎臟。
It coagulates the kidneys and you get kidney trouble.
它會使腎臟凝結，導致腎臟問題。
You cannot pass urine and you have all the troubles there.
尿液不能通過，那你會有很多問題。
Apart from that, it goes to the lower intestines and you get terrible constipations and all
除此之外，它會進入大腸，你會得到嚴重的便秘和所有
the problems of the constipation.
便秘的問題。
Then also to the heart at a later age it comes.
然後到了晚年，心臟也隨之而來。
It goes on affecting.
它繼續影響。
Ultimately your heart fails very early in age.
最終在你年輕時，心臟就已不行了。
I know of, recently, two people died of heart trouble who were at a very good position.
我知道，最近有兩個人死於心臟病，他們都有很好的職位。
This is very much worrying Me that how to bring them to close to themselves, to know
我非常擔心如何讓他們更瞭解自己，知道
themselves what’s the problem is and how to solve that problem.
他們自己的問題是什麼，以及如何解決。
With this we understand that we react, by reaction we create such a heat within us.
以此就會明白，我們對事物的反應，在反作用力下我們體內部便產生熱。
Apart from this, the other psychosomatic diseases, this is the, I am telling you about somatic,
除此之外，其他的心身疾病，我只說了關於身體的，
but the psycho disease which comes from your psychological problems come from the left
而心理疾病是來自左脈你的心理精神
side.
問題。
Of course I’ll not deal with that now.
當然，我不會現在處理這個問題。
But somehow, if you can move from right to the left, you are sure to get some psychosomatic
然而，如果你從右傾轉向左傾，你肯定會得到一些
trouble which cannot be cured by medical science, like cancer, aches, all kinds of this.
醫學沒法治癒的身心失調病證，如各樣不同的癌症，疼痛等。
So you are just preparing your body for that.
所以為此你要讓身體作好準備。
In these modern times, the life is so full of struggle, speed.
現代生活充滿競爭及速度。
Now we were coming and there was a jam.
當我們正在前來的時候發生交通擠塞。
Now you can’t help it.
你會無能為力。
I was very silently watching, “Now this, the jam, I have to reach late, doesn’t matter.”
我很靜地看著想，「現在塞車，必會遲到，但無關緊要。」
My husband normally would’ve been really in great trouble.
而我丈夫通常會非常焦躁。
He would’ve looked at the watch all the time.
他會一直看著手錶。
Would have been “Where are we?
原本應該「我們在哪裡？
What are we doing?” this and that.
我們在做什麼？」這樣那樣。
But he was so silently watching the whole thing, I was amazed because normally he would
但是他卻靜觀整個事情，我很驚訝，因為通常他會
be jittering that we are getting so late for a function like.
因為遲到了一個約會而緊張。
Now, you see, once you get rid of this problem, is the easiest thing to live.
現在你看，一旦擺脫了這個問題，生活便變得從容。
The other day I met one gentleman who was transferred.
有一天，我遇到了一位男仕被調動。
He said “Always whenever!”
他說「總是要這樣！」
He is an IAS officer, “Whenever I am transferred, Mother, I used to be so jittery.
他是國際會計準則官員，「母親，每當我被調動，我就會緊張。
Such tension, such stress on my mind, baba.
這種緊張，壓力在我心中，喋喋不休。
What will happen?
之後會發生什麼？
Where will the children go?
孩子們該去哪兒？
What will happen to the house?
房子會怎麼樣？
This, that, all problems would come to me.
這樣那樣，所有問題都會發生在我身上。
But what has happened to me and my wife, we don’t feel anything now.
但是我和妻子發生了什麼事，我們現在都沒有感覺了。
We don’t feel.
我們沒有感覺。
We are not worried.
我們並不擔心。
We sleep very well.”
我們睡得很好。
I said, “That’s what has to happen.
我說，「這事本應如此發生。
All these things should not affect you.”
所有這些都不應該影響你。」
That’s only possible when you can go beyond this mind, which we think.
這只有能突破我們想像出來的思維才可能發生。
Mind is a, not such a good word, I should say because it’s not mental.
我應該說，「思維」 可能用詞不當，因為並不是指精神上的。
It is, if it is only mind means the one which thinks and for them mental hospital is also
它是，如果它只是思維意指那想像出來的，那對他們來說整個精神病院都是
mad people.
瘋子。
I don’t know how English language moves, it’s difficult you know.
我不知道英語是如何操作，你很難清楚理解。
English language is very difficult to explain Sahaja Yoga because in the English language
以英語來解釋霎哈嘉瑜伽是很困難，因為在英語中
you’ll be amazed that they call ‘spirit’.
你會驚訝他們所稱謂的「靈 (spirit)」。
‘Spirit’ is the Atma, right, ‘spirit’ is the dead body moving about according to
「Spirit」是Atma(靈) ，依他們來說「Spirit」 可以是「亡靈」
them and thirdly it means also alcohol.
第三解釋，是指「酒精」。
Now which one is closer to which one, I don’t know, but this is why I am saying that English
我真不知道那個意思會比較接近，但這就是我說英語
language is a difficult thing.
會辭不達意的意思。
Marathi is the best because lot of work has been done among Maharashtrians on Kundalini.
馬拉地語最好，因為馬哈拉施特拉邦人已完整了很多昆達裡尼(Kundalini)的工作。
Nath Panthis were there.
通過冥想作修行的人仕(Nath Panthis)在那裡。
They have done lot of work.
他們做了很多工作。
But the tradition was that one person would give Realization to only one person.
但傳統是，一個人只會向一個人開啟自覺。
If I have done anything you think worth mentioning, it is that I tried to find out a way of giving
如果我做了你認為值得一提的事情，那就是我試圖找到一種給予
collective Realization, collective happening.
集體實現自覺的方式，集體地發生。
That’s what was My humble contribution and by which I find thousands of people have got
這就是我卑微的貢獻，並且我使成千上萬的人
their Realization.
得到他們的自覺。
Now what is the Realization?
現在什麼是自覺？
It is that if you see at the base of the spinal chord is a triangular bone called as ‘Sacrum’.
如果你觀察脊柱的底部，會看到一個稱為「 薦骨」的三角骨。
It is called ‘Sacrum’ because it is a sacred bone and the Greeks knew about it,
它被稱為'Sacrum'，因為它是一個神聖的骨頭，這希臘人已知道，
that it’s a sacred bone.
那是一個神聖的骨頭。
And according to our Shastras and also many other prophecies, there resides a power within
根據我們的聖典以及許多其他預言，有一個力量存在於
us, our own power, your own power called as Kundalini.
我們之內，屬於自己的力量，那力量叫做昆達裡尼。
Is called ‘Kundalini’ because it is in three and a half coils.
被稱為'Kundalini'，因為它呈三圈半捲曲。
Coils are called ‘kundal’, that’s why it is the Kundalini.
捲曲稱為'kundal'，這就是稱為昆達利尼(Kundalini)的原因。
Now this, this power is your own.
現在，這個力量是你自己的。
It’s in every human being and if it is awakened, it passes through six centers piercing through
它存在於每個人身上，如果它被喚醒，它會穿過六個中心再穿過
the top of the head, which we call as the Brahmarandhra in the Sanskrit language and
頭頂－我們梵文稱之為Brahmarandhra
the fontanel area in the English language.
英語稱為fontanel(腦囟)。
It passes through that soft bone which was there in the childhood and you just start
它穿過童年時代的還是軟骨的位置，你便開始
feeling the cool breeze coming out of your head and the cool breeze coming on to your
感受到微微涼風從你的頭頂冒出來，然後涼風來到你的
fingertips.
指尖。
It happens.
它是這樣發生。
It’s an experience and for which you cannot pay.
這是無論你付出任何代價都不能交換到的體驗。
You cannot.
你不能。
I may go on telling you lots of stories this, that, that won’t work out.
我可能會繼續告訴你很多這樣那樣的故事，那不能成就。
It has to happen.
它必會發生。
The Kundalini has to rise and has to pierce through fontanel area otherwise, otherwise,
昆達利尼必須上升，然後穿過腦囟，否則，
it’s no use.
這是沒有作用的。
It’s just words, some sermon or something like that.
這只是文字，一些說教或類似的東西。
So this happening is very easy in this Kaliyuga.
在Kaliyuga迦利(紛亂)時期這是非常容易發生。
Is really remarkable because maybe because of Kaliyug people are fed up of the things
或許是因為紛亂期人厭倦了正在發生的事情，所以
going on and all kinds of things working out.
各種各樣的成就都發生得非常明顯。
Now what does it do?
它做了什麼呢？
It passes through six center.
它通過了六個中心。
Six centers, these are meant for our physical, mental, and emotional being and also for our
六個能量中心，意指我們的身體，精神和情感的存有，也是
spiritual being.
靈性上的存有。
So when it passes through these six centers, it nourishes those centers, it integrates
因此，當它通過這六個中心時，它會滋養其中，整合
all these centers, and ultimately it passes through this and enters into the all pervading
所有這些中心，最終它通過這個並進入無所不在的
power of Divine love, is called as ‘Paramchaitanya’.
被稱為「Paramchaitanya」神聖之愛的力量。
You may call it as ‘all pervading power of Divine love’ or anything but names make
你可稱為「神聖的無所不在的愛的力量」或者任何無所稱謂的
no difference.
也沒有分別。
There is a very subtle power around us, which looks after us, which guides us, which helps
我們周圍有一種非常微妙的力量，它照顧著我們，引導著我們，幫助我們
us, which is the torsion area.
就是這扭力場區。
Now, while doing that what happens that you become knowledgeable of the absolute truth,
當這樣發生的同事，你會變得明白絕對真理，
absolute!
絕對！
Whatever you know is absolute, is nothing to doubt, nothing can be challenged.
你知道所有絕對的事，無疑惑，沒有可以被挑戰。
For example, it starts flowing through your fingertips.
例如，它開始流通你的指尖。
Starts flowing through your fingertips and you can feel it on your fingertips, your centers.
開始流過指尖，您可以在指尖和各能量中心感受它。
Now these are five, six, and seven centers, five, six and seven centers.
這是5，6和7能量中心，5，6和7能量中心。
I am not going to tell you all the details now.
我現在不打算告訴你所有的細節。
But when you start feeling these whole sensation, Adi Shankaracharya has called it as ‘spand’,
但當你開始感受到這種完全知覺，商羯羅 (大師)稱之為'spand(輕微震動)'，
then you feel the truth, the real truth.
然後你就會感受到真理，真正的真理。
For example, supposing in your office you get somebody who is a cheat, very well dressed,
例如，假設在你的辦公室裡，你遇到一個騙子，衣著得體，
speaks English very well, you know, very well behaved.
說得一口流利英語，談吐儀態也很好。
How will you make him out?
你怎麼把他分辨出來呢？
Just have to put your hands under your table and see for yourself.
只需將手放在桌子下面，親自看看。
Immediately you will get some sort of a burning sensation or you might feel some sort of a,
你會立刻得到某種灼熱的感覺，或者你可能會感覺到某種感覺，
what do you call, needle and pins like that.
你會稱為，類似被針刺或釘的感覺。
That kind of a feeling you might get.
你會感到類似的感覺。
Then you will also know what centers he’s catching on your fingertips.
然後你會從指尖感覺到他那個輪穴被感染。
This is the absolute knowledge about everything.
這是對一切事物的絕對知識。
Is not question of only knowing he is a bad or a good person, but also of diseases.
不僅僅是知道他是好或壞人，而且還有疾病。
Supposing you have some disease, you will feel it on your fingertips.
假設你有一些疾病，你會從指尖感覺到它。
On your fingertips you’ll feel it.
你會在指尖感受到它。
You’ll know this is your disease and if you know how to cure them, you can cure others
你會知道你的疾病，如果你懂如何治癒它，你就可以治癒別人
also because you become one with the whole.
也因為你成為整體之一
It’s a very collective personality you develop.
你會發展出非常群體的個性。
Who is the other, after all?
畢竟誰是以外的？
We are all one.
我們是合一的。
But only trouble is we are separated because of this ignorance.
但唯一問題是我們因為無知而分開了。
Once this works out, so many things drop out from us.
一旦這個問題解決了，很多事情會從我們身上消失。
This is the right side I am telling you about but also the conditionings are very much working
這是我告訴你有關右脈的，但制約也對我們
out in us.
產生很大作用。
In our reaction, there are two things that work out.
在我們的反應中，有兩件事會產生。
One is the right side, another the left side.
一個是右脈，另一個是左脈。
And the left side is all the conditioning as you see there.
左脈你看到所有制約。
These conditionings come to us through our childhood, through our family, through our
這些制約來自我們的童年，家庭，
country, through our reading, this, that all kinds of things, they come up.
國家，閱讀，以及各種各樣的事情。
But also family upbringing is very important because according to our Shaastraas, there
但家庭教養也非常重要，因為根據印度古典籍記載，那裡
are six enemies.
存在六大敵人。
We have got six.
我們有六個。
Now these six enemies are what?
這六大敵人是什麼？
So Kama, Krodha, Mada, Matsara, Lobha, Moha.
是Kama，Krodha，Mada，Matsara，Lobha，Moha。
Kama is what you can call sexual urge.
Kama是你所謂的性衝動。
Krodha is anger.
Krodha是憤怒。
Krishna has denounced anger.
Krishna(克裡希納)有斥責惡行的怒氣。
But all right sided people are hot tempered.
但是，所有右傾的人都脾氣暴躁。
They don’t want to be, but they are.
他們不想成為這樣，但他們是。
And when they lose their temper then they feel bad also.
當他們發脾氣後他們也感覺不好。
Not that they want to lose it but they just lose it.
並不他們想發脾氣，但他們就是發了出來。
Now this one drops out.
現在這個也退掉了。
The temper goes out completely because you develop that witness state saakshi swaroopa.
因為你發展出saakshi swaroopa(旁觀見證者之反映)，脾氣暴躁會離你而去
With that witness state you just see everything.
憑藉那種見證狀態，你能看到一切。
You don’t lose temper.
你不會發脾氣。
You just see it.
你只會看著它。
That is one thing drops out very well.
這是一件非常好的事情。
Mada is false pride.
Mada是妄自尊大。
That we have.
我們有這個。
I know IAS officers and their wives.
我知道IAS官員和他們的妻子。
They have that false pride.
他們有這種妄自尊大。
Not everyone, but some of them do, they have.
不是每個人，但他們中的一些人有。
I have very funny experiences of that.
我有非常有趣的經歷。
Like, once we went to Delhi to Hatriji and they had given us a house in Mina Bagh and
就像，有一次我們去德裡(Delhi)到Hatriji，他們在Mina Bagh安排了給了一間屋給我們
I met another friend of Mine from Lucknow who had married an IAS officer.
同時我到勒克瑙(Lucknow)探望另一位與IAS軍官結婚的朋友。
Oh, very proud girl and she asked Me, “Where are you living?
那非常自豪的女孩問我，「哦！你住在哪裡？
How are you?”
你好嗎？」
I said, “My husband is a government servant and so he’s transferred here.”
我說，「我的丈夫是政府人員，他被調到這裡。」
“But where are you living?”
「但你住在哪裡？」
I said “Mina Bagh.”
我說「Mina Bagh」
“Oh my God!
「哦，我的天啊！
Mina Bagh!
Mina Bagh！
What is your husband doing?
你丈夫是什麼職位？
Is he a clerk?
他是文員嗎？
What is he doing?”
他是做什麼的？」
I said, “He’s doing something” and I was just looking at her the way she was on
我說，「他正在辦點事」，我就像她看著我一樣
Me.
望著她。
“My husband might be your husband’s boss” this and that.
「我的丈夫可能是你丈夫的上司」這樣那樣的。
I said, “Maybe I don’t know anything about these things.
我說，「我對這些事情也不知道。
I am sorry, I don’t know your list of people, anything.
對不起，我不認識你提到的人員名單，或什麼的。
I am not interested.”
我沒興趣。」
And then My husband came.
然後我的丈夫來了。
So she said, “See that tall man.
然後她說，「看看那個高個子男人。
You know he’s very important.
你知道他很重要的人物。
He’s with the Prime Minister.
他與首相一起的。
You go and talk to him and get Your husband promoted.”
你去跟他談談，讓你的丈夫提升職位吧。」
I said ([Laughing] What is she up to?), I said, “Sudhali, he is My husband.”
我回應（[笑了]她在做什麼？），我說，「Sudhali，他是我的丈夫。」
“Heh!
「嘿！
He’s your husband?
他是你的丈夫？
Haan yaar!
哈…呀！
Oh my God!
哦，我的天呀！
I am sorry I am.”
我很抱歉。」
I said, “It’s all right.”
我說，「沒關係。」
Common experience.
相同經歷。
The women also become IAS, you see, not actually but as wives and I’ve been such a lost person
你看，那女仕也成了IAS人員，不是實際上的，作為人妻而我一直跟她們一樣
with them.
迷失其中。
I could never understand what is there to be IAS and to be his wife.
我永遠無法理解作為IAS以及他妻子的意義。
It was beyond Me.
它超越了我的範圍。
But one thing, what really helped Me in all this turmoil of life, because you know our
但有一點，在所有這些混亂生活中真正幫助我的是什麼，因為你知道我們的
pay is less, this, that all problems are there, was the patriotism Raashtra Bhakti.
薪水較少，這就是主要的問題，作為民族愛國主義者。
My father was a great patriot.
我的父親是一位偉大的愛國者。
My mother was.
我媽媽也是。
They sacrificed everything for the independence of this country.
為了這個國家的獨立，他們犧牲了一切。
I cannot travel by any foreign airlines, whatever maybe.
無論如何，我都不能乘坐任何外國航空公司。
Maybe Air India is not good, doesn’t matter.
也許印度航空不好，沒關係。
It’s My, My country’s.
這是我的，我的國家。
So the feeling that this is My country kept Me going.
因此，這我的國家的感覺讓我繼續前進。
You see you become like a Kargil soldier.
你看，你變得像一個卡吉爾(Kargil)士兵。
You are fighting for your country.
你正為你的國家而戰。
You are working for your country.
你為自己的國家工作。
My husband got into Indian Foreign Service.
我的丈夫進入了印度外交部。
I told him, “Nothing doing.
我告訴他，「辦不到。
We don’t drink, both of us and I can’t leave My country in the lurch at the time
我兩不喝酒，當我們獲得自由的時候，我不能
when we have got the freedom.
在危難中離開我的國家
So if you want you can go, I will not come.
所以，如果你想要你可以去，我不會來。
I don’t want to go to Foreign Service.”
我不想去外交部。」
They cut his pay.
他被削減了工資。
That time, you know, 300 was a big amount.
那個時候，你知道，300是一個很大的數額。
I said, “Doesn’t matter.
我說，「沒關係，
Whatever it is, I’ll stay in My country.
不管什麼，我會留在我的國家。
I’ll work in My country and you work here.
我將在我的國家工作，你在這裡工作，
I’ll support you every way.
我會一路支持你，
I don’t want anything.
我並無他求，
Nothing I want and you don’t take a bribe at all otherwise that day I’ll leave this.”
我不要什麼，你根本就不會收受賄賂，否則那天我會離開這個。」
Otherwise also I said that, “The another thing is our country has to develop.”
另外我也說過，「另一件事是我們國家必需發展。」
Who will develop?
誰來發展？
I always felt that you are the spinal cord of our country.
我一直覺得你是我們國家的棟樑。
You have to develop this country.
你必需發展這個國家。
What is this money?
金錢是什麼？
Comes and goes.
來來去去的。
You’ve seen the people who have got money, where their children have gone?
你見過那些有錢的人，他們的孩子去了哪裡？
What has happened to them?
他們發生了什麼事？
What have they achieved?
他們取得了什麼成果？
So I told very frankly that I will not go to the Foreign Service of any kind because
所以我坦率地告訴我，我不會去什麼外交部門，因為
what is in the Foreign Service?
外交部算是什麼？
I want to do everything in this country of Mine for which I have also fought.
我想在我的國家盡一切努力。
I have fought a lot and this is what now sometimes, you know, is disappointing to see what things
我做過了很多抗爭，所以你會知道當看到正發生的事
are happening.
是何等令人失望。
But a day will come.
但那一天會到來。
This country will rise.
這個國家將會崛起。
How?
如何達到？
Because when this happens, when this Kundalini rising take place, when people become realized
因為當這情況發生時，當昆達裡尼(Kundalini)升起，人們就會成為
souls, they just transform.
自覺的靈，他們會轉化。
They become extremely patriotic, extremely patriotic and they understand what is needed
他們變得極為愛國，非常愛國，他們會理解我們的國家
today for our country.
今天所需要的。
They can sacrifice anything.
他們可以犧牲任何東西。
They can live anywhere and they are not bothered about some sort of a, you can call it a financial
他們可以住在任何地方，他們不會為某種形式而煩惱，你可以稱之為財務方面
help or other material thing.
幫助或其他物質的東西。
They are above materialism.
他們超越了唯物主義。
There are thousands and thousands like that even in our country, thousands and also abroad.
即使在我們國家，成千上萬，也有國外，成千上萬的人。
Now Sahaja Yoga is working 86 countries.
現在霎哈嘉瑜伽正在86個國家工作。
They are all full of joy because with this happening you get joy of a quality which has
他們都很高興，因為有了這個你會得到一種
no double thing.
沒有雙重意義的快樂。
It’s not happiness / unhappiness.
這不是 快樂 與 不快樂。
It’s just joy and you have another thing also with it, is the peace of mind.
只有快樂，還有另外一件事，就是心裡平靜。
Just you are so peaceful, absolutely peaceful.
你會變得如此平靜，絕對平靜。
You don’t have to worry about things.
你不必擔心任何事。
You don’t have to become jittery because see the diseases you develop.
你不必因為看到你所患的疾病而感到緊張。
Apart from that, all kinds of paralysis comes on us.
除此之外，還不用擔心各樣的癱瘓症發生在身上。
We had a doctor in our hospital there who was working very hard.
我們在醫院裡有一位很勤力的醫生。
I told him that, “Doctor, see now your age has come.
我告訴他，「醫生，你的年齡都不輕了。
You should take it easy.
你應該放輕鬆一下。
Daytime you must rest.
白天你必須休息。
There’s no need.
沒有必要。
You are not in a office, just rest, take rest do something else.
你不在辦公室時要休息，或休息下來做別的事情。
Read or you can go and play.
閱讀或你可以去玩。
Do something.”
做點其他事。」
He wouldn’t listen to Me and then he got paraplegia, means that failure of the hand
他不會聽我，後來他半身不遂，手腳都
and the leg, completely.
完全不能動。
He couldn’t even walk.
他甚至不能走路。
He couldn’t lift his leg.
他無法提起他的腿。
Now he’s all right, cured.
現在他沒事，治癒了。
But then I told him that you take treatment for your right side.
但後來我告訴他你因為過於右脈才需接受治療。
That’s very important.
這非常重要。
It’s very simple treatment and which can be done very easily.
這是非常簡單的治療，可以很容易做到。
For example, you can have an ice bag on the liver.
例如，你可以在肝臟上放一個冰墊。
You can have ice bag here because this is the portion.
你可以放一個冰墊在這裡，因為這個部分。
This moves like this so the portion this one gets heated up.
這樣的行徑使這個部分變熱了。
So you put ice here, you put ice.
所以你把冰放在這裡，你放冰。
This icing business will really help you a lot.
這敷冰方法可幫你許多。
But also there are some other very simple homely treatments which you can take.
也有些其他非常簡單的家常療法，你可以採取。
But I would request all of you to come to our center somewhere in
但我會要求你們所有人來到我們的中心
Mother talks aside: [Bhaaratiya?
和旁邊的人對話：[Bhaaratiya？
Wahan hai na?
Wahan hai na？
Bharatiya, usmein hai ki nahi?]
Bharatiya，usmein hai ki nahi？]
Where is she gone?
她去了哪裡？
Somebody says, “Bhaaratiya Vidya Peeth.”
有人回答，「Bhaaratiya Vidya Peeth。」
Shri Mataji: So you all can come there if you live in this area.
錫呂.瑪塔吉女仕：如果你住在這個地區，你們都可以來這裡。
In every area, we have got centers.
在每個地區，我們都有中心。
So you all can come into that center humbly.
所以你們都可以虛心地到那個中心。
There is, you see, in Sahaja Yoga there is nothing like any position or anything.
你知道，在霎哈嘉瑜伽中，沒有什麼職位階級之分。
We have to humble down.
我們必須謙卑下來。
This false pride is of no use.
妄自尊大是無用處的。
We humble down.
我們要謙卑下來。
When we humble down, it’s very easy to achieve it and to get this into yourself.
當我們謙卑下來時，它會非常容易達到及融入自己。
After all, otherwise, what is it?
否則，它還會是什麼？
What is life for?
生命是什麼？
There’s no enjoyment.
如果不能享受。
There’s no experiencing of what you are doing.
沒有經歷過，那你在做什麼。
So much work you put in I know, I know that.
我知道你安排了很多工作，我理解。
I know how you people have to work hard.
我知道你們何等努力工作。
But to get over, to get over all the strain and stress, you must do meditation for five
但要擺脫，要超越所有緊張和壓力，你必須冥想
minutes which they will tell you how to do it.
5分鐘，他們會告訴你如何做。
Five minutes in the evening will help you.
晚上五分鐘便會幫助你。
So, just like as you take bath in the morning, bathe yourself with the showers of this Kundalini.
所以，就像你早上洗澡一樣，以昆達裡尼為自己淋浴。
She’s your mother.
她是你的母親。
She has been your mother from ages and she has recorded everything about you within itself.
多年來她一直是你的母親，她記錄了你自己的一切。
This is the subtle side of you and when you want to have your Realization, she’s very
這是你精微的一面，當你想得到自覺，她就
anxious to be awakened.
渴望被喚醒。
She’s extremely anxious and it works wonders.
她非常渴望，它奇跡地成就了。
I am surprised that how people get Realization in no time.
我很驚訝人們是如何在很短的時間內獲得自覺。
The only trouble with them is, it’s like a primule or you can call it the ‘ankuraa’,
對他們來說唯一問題就是，它像一個報春花，或者你可以稱之為'ankuraa' (掛鉤)，
which grows but it doesn’t become a tree.
它生長但它不會成為一棵樹。
So, little bit you have to meditate.
所以，你必須一點點地靜坐。
You have to be collective and works out.
你必須在集體內並努力。
In collective, you forget everything, your position everything.
在集體中，你會忘記一切，你的一切職位。
I have known IAS officers who have been dancing with the villagers, singing with the villagers,
我認識IAS官員和村民一起跳舞，一起唱歌，
so much they enjoy.
他們非常喜歡。
They said, “We knew this but we never wanted to express it, you see.”
他們說，「這些我們都知道，但從不想表達出來。」
So all this drops out.
所有這一切都放下了。
All these outward bondages drop out and you become one with the collective.
所有這些外在的束縛都消失了，你就會與集體合一。
You know their problems.
你知道他們的問題。
You know how to solve them and it’s very good.
你知道如把它們解決，這非常好。
I think this is what is only one has to achieve, nothing else.
我認為這是唯一一個必須達到的，沒有別的。
If you achieve this, you’ve achieved the last and the best.
如果你達成了這目標，那麼便算你已經取得最後成績。
With this then you can help others.
你可以以這個幫助別人。
You can give Realizations to others.
您可以給其他人自覺。
You can save their lives.
你可以拯救他們的生命。
I mean, it’s all your power that is going to work out.
我的意思是，你所有的力量都會發揮作用。
In these days of horrible struggle and all kinds of things happening, violence, very
在這些可怕的鬥爭和各種各樣事情，暴力發生的日子裡
much needed is this Sahaja Yoga.
非常需要霎哈嘉瑜伽。
And you’ll be amazed, it is something a grace that people get it.
而且你會感到驚訝，人們得到它是一個恩典。
In Turkey, we have about two thousand people who are realized souls.
在土耳其，我們有大約兩千人是得到了自覺的靈。
Nobody lost their life, not a single thing, not their houses were even, they just little
沒有人失去生命或任何事物，甚或他們的房子，他們只有一點點
bit, I would say, shook but never fell down.
動搖，我會這樣說，但從未跌倒過。
The whole Orissa, it happened the same.
整個奧裡薩邦(Orissa)，也如此發生。
It has happened in several places that people have been just saved with those who have been
在許多地方都發生，人們剛剛和那些蒙神恩典的人
in the grace of the Divine.
一同得救。
We have to become that.
我們必會成為那樣。
We can’t live without it.
生命裡不能沒有它。
It’s rather subtle.
這是相當精微的。
It is subtle, I know but sometimes must understand we have to be subtle.
它很精微，而有時我們必須變得精微的。
Now as it is, so much of illness, sickness I find, mostly I find with all the people
現在的情況是，我們發現了很多患病的人
who are working very hard is the right sided problem.
他們都是右脈得很厲害。
Some sort of a right side.
整體是右傾的。
And it can be absolutely cured, absolutely be under your control, and you can cure others
它絕對可以治癒，絕對在你的控制之下，你亦可以
also.
治癒別人。
This is such a blessing we have in this horrible Kaliyuga.
這是我們在這個可怕的混亂期(Kaliyuga)中所擁有的祝福。
The worst times, they say, the worst and worst that is the time is now and you see the effects
他們說，這是最糟糕最壞的時候，你看到發生
of that.
什麼事。
But in that only, the lotus of Sahaja Yoga has come up.
但與此同時，霎哈嘉瑜伽的蓮花才出現。
You don’t have to pay for it.
你不需要付費。
That’s one thing you should know.
這是你應該知道的事。
Anybody asks money from you, he’s not Divine.
任何有人向你要錢，他都不神聖。
Don’t have to pay for it, at all.
根本不用付錢。
When you grow and when you achieve, when you give Realizations to others, then you will
當你成長，成就，當你給別人自覺，那麼你會
be surprised you rise into a new realm of understanding which is a doubtless awareness
感到驚訝，你會進入一個新的理解領域，這是無疑惑的醒覺狀態
which is called as ‘Nirvikalpa Samadhi’ according to Patanjali.
根據印度聖哲帕坦伽利(Patanjali)，它被稱為'Nirvikalpa Samadhi'(無疑惑 三摩地)境界。
Now as we have learnt English, I don’t think we read much of the, our Indian scriptures
現在我們學習英語，我們不會多閱讀印度經典
and thing.
和事情。
But that also, those who read will go on praying to one monde of statues, this, that, I mean
而那些有閱讀經典的，又會拜偶像，這個那個的，我的意思
just they are fanatically religious people, wasting their life like that.
是他們是宗教狂熱人士，浪費他們的生命。
The another side are the buddhivaadis what you call are the intellectuals, you see.
另一邊是buddhivaadis你稱之為知識分子，你看。
They are the much worst because they think they have read everything.
他們更糟糕，因為他們以為已經閱讀了所有知識。
They know everything.
他們已知道一切。
Now what to tell them?
現在告訴他們什麼？
It’s a very simple thing, they don’t want to accept.
這事情太簡單，他們不想接受。
You can’t tell them, “Take it straight.”
你不能告訴他們，「直接說吧。」
You have to have it in the other way.
你須以另一種方式獲得它。
So also to understand it, we should know we have not known ourselves.
所以也要瞭解，我們其實還不很瞭解自己。
We have to know ourselves and for knowing ourselves, Kundalini awakening is the only
我們必須瞭解自己，而以我所知，為了這樣喚醒昆達裡尼
way, as far as I know.
是唯一的方式。
And I hope you all will think about it and come to our centers where Realization can
我希望你們都會考慮一下，然後我們的中心
be given.
來獲取自覺。
There are many centers we have got.
我們有很多中心。
You don’t have to pay any money, nothing, but you come and relax.
你不需要付錢，什麼也不需要，但你要輕鬆的來到。
Relaxation is only possible after Self-Realization, not before that.
只有在得到視覺後才能放鬆，而不是在此之前。
You’ll be surprised your aging will stop.
你會驚訝於你會停止衰老。
I have no aging problem.
我沒有年老問題。
My husband also has no aging problem.
我丈夫也沒有年老問題。
We don’t think of it.
我們沒有想及它。
It’s over.
這結束了。
Now, whenever one has to die, one will die.
現在，必會死亡的都將會死去。
But till then we are not bothered.
但在那之前，我們並不擔心。
Anything that you do will have a special light of the Divine.
你做的每件事都會有特別神聖的光芒。
I bless you from My heart that you develop this subtle things within yourself and you
我衷心祝福你們，能在你的內在發展這精微的事
try to understand that so far you have not known yourself.
同時瞭解那從未瞭解過的自己。
You have to know yourself.
你必須瞭解自己。
You don’t have to introspect and sit down criticizing yourself, feeling guilty.
你不需反省，坐下來批判自己或感到內疚。
No, not at all.
一點都不要。
Whatever has happened has happened because you’ll be amazed at yourself that all your
所有該發生都會發生，你會對自己感到驚訝，
destructive habits also will drop out by themselves.
所有的壞習慣也會自己改掉。
Overnight in London, there were twelve boys with the addiction of drugs.
在倫敦 一夜之間，有十二個吸毒成癮的男孩。
They stopped over night, over night.
他們一夜之間戒掉了。
I don’t, never told them.
我沒叫他們要這樣做。
I never tell people, “Don’t, don’t.”
我從不告訴別人，「不要這，不要那。」
I never say that.
我從來不會這樣說。
But that Kundalini rises and the light of the, your heart, light of the Spirit, that
但當昆達裡尼上升了，你內心的光，心靈的亮光
guides you.
會給你指引。
That tells you what is destructive for you.
它會告訴你有什麼對你有害處。
And you have power not to accept anything that is destructive.
你有權拒絕那些對你有害的東西。
I know there are difficulties.
我知道這有困難。
I know there are problems but you’ll never see them.
我知道有問題，但你永遠不會察覺它們。
If you are sitting in a boat, you are not be bothered as to how deep the sea is.
比喻你坐在船上，你不會困擾於海有多深。
It’s like that.
這個就像。
You rise above all these things and you watch and you help others.
你超越所有這些東西，你看見並幫助別人。
Apart from that, it helps you in your work, very much in your work.
除此之外，它還可以幫助你的工作，非常有助於你的工作。
You understand your work very well because of torsion area again.
由於扭力場，你很瞭解你的工作。
My husband says, “How do You get this idea?”
我的丈夫說：「你怎麼有這個主意？」
I say, “I got it.
我說，「我就是知道。
All right this is the idea, I’ve got it.”
好吧！這就是這個想法，我明白了。」
Now he’s amazed sometimes how I manage things.
現在他有時會驚訝於我如何管理事物。
How I am doing?
我處理得好嗎？
I have no secretariat.
我沒有秘書處。
I have no secretary.
我沒有秘書。
I have no P.A., nothing.
我沒有私人助理，沒有。
And we are working in 86 countries.
我們在86個國家開展工作。
So it is just works out because it is this Divine power which is so helpful or which
之所以能成功，是因為這神聖的力量是如此有幫助
is so kind.
及如此有善